Uh, I think we stopped at 3:32, you
guys. Am I
right?
Really? I
[Music]
um Yeah, that's okay. Uh, I don't mind
to start there. Okay. Uh, then the lady
says, "Who she talking to for zero
dollars?"
The devil. Yeah.
ignorance. Misunderstanding.
Misunderstanding. She's talking
misunder. And she says, "By the way, I
heard you guys finish
some
images for flow dot, right? And I heard
I get to see them tomorrow. Is that
right?" From each house. And I heard it
went very well, but I will judge
tomorrow. Okay.
Uh, so yeah, she calls him arrogant. You
think you're a master. You're not a
master. Uh, you lack No, we did cover
this. You lack good qualities and you
don't have the the things that bring you
those good qualities like meditation.
All right. Now, we'll start on 332.
Uh you say that nothing depends on
anything else. You say that things are
unchanging. You say they are firm and
they you say they are solid. Did he say
that? Does does the bad part of your own
mind does it think nothing's going to
change?
Not directly. Good answer. Over there is
some guy over there. Uh yeah, of of
course you understand things change, you
know, like I don't know, you get hungry
after lunch and they make you sit in
these long classes and you get more and
more hungry. You're hungry changes,
right? Nobody can say things don't
change. Uh ignorance doesn't say things
don't change. He does. He never said
that. Why is she accusing him of
that? My teacher in the Gishi course if
one person give all the
answers he will say did you elect him to
answer all your
questions for you? Yeah they
did.
Okay.
Anyway, listen. If things are not coming
from your seeds, if things are not come
from from your seeds, they would never
change. In your mind, you think things
are coming from the outside to the
inside. 100 bucks for the Tibetan word.
Not
you. Huh?
I unelected him.
In this country, you can win the most
votes and you still don't get to be
president.
Is it Dongzen?
Huh? What? Dongzen. No. Come on. Den,
the person who thinks everything is
coming this way. Gizen knows everything.
He's your student.
Sirong over here. You got 100 bucks.
[Applause]
Yeah. So means uh incoming. Okay.
Incoming from the object to the eye.
Okay. Tong means that's how you see
things. So what's an arya?
Arya means somebody who's touched the
diamond world directly. We saw emptiness
directly. Okay. And then
uh is the opposite. Son means not Arya.
They think the world is coming this way.
They don't understand the world is
coming this way. Okay. Which leads me to
another
question. How's my cash doing? Right.
It's all right. Okay. I trust you.
Uh ready. This is easy money. You're
gonna if your family says, "Why you took
a week off to go diamond mountain?" You
can say, "I made more money than at my
job."
Okay, here's the question. You ready?
How many times in the diamond cutter
Sutra does it mention diamond?
Raise your hand. Zero.
Who said? Y'all say don't.
Okay. 100 bucks.
What I'm trying to say is the Okay.
Since you're the exyear director of this
place, uh you can answer two more
questions for the money. Uh what's the
Sanskrit for diamond and what's the
English word related to it?
Sanskrit word is bajra. Yeah. Badra
which means power. Instrument of power.
Budra.
And oh si veggies. Yeah. Vegetable.
Okay. Vegetable. Uh.
Okay. Why? In in ancient times uh they
agreed with my
wife and uh they said vegetables make
you powerful, vegetables make you
strong. Okay, they believe that in
ancient times I mean not
nowadays.
Okay, so anyway Bajra okay it's anytime
you see diamond anytime you see somebody
talking about diamond uh you have to ask
why is everybody talking about diamonds?
Okay, now you're in a diamond way class.
Diamond way person means suspicious
person, you know. Oh, Buddhist trying to
send me a message. Somebody asked you
why they call it diamond cutter sutra
and you say it's a message. Okay,
understand that's diamond way. Answer.
Does the diamond and diamond cutter
sutra have anything to do with diamond
way?
You're spo, you know, if you're not in a
diamond way clash, you're supposed to
say,
"Uhuh." And if you are in a diamond way
clash, you're supposed to say, "Of
course." It's some kind of message.
Okay. All right. Got
it.
Anyway, if someone could give me I don't
know, it's too much money, but um let's
just answer a question without money.
Okay.
Uh, she accuses the devil that he
believes nothing ever changes. He
believes that. She says you believe
nothing ever changes. Why would she say
that?
That say it into the microphone just for
your teacher and not
for financial gain.
[Music]
with Henry.
May May I
get there's certain people have to pay
the teacher
$100 to give an
answer? No. Okay. Okay. Now, don't
forget the question. The question is,
why does the angel accuse
misunderstanding?
Why does she tell him you think nothing
changes? Of course, he doesn't think
that. We, you and me, we we lived for
many years without touching the diamond
world. Maybe then why does why do we
believe nothing changes? Because we can
see things change every moment.
Um, she's accusing the devil of falling
into one of the extremes of falling into
one of the extremes. uh the extreme
view. If you think things are
self-existent
uh coming from their own side, then the
result of that belief must be that
things don't change. So therefore, if
he's saying things are the way they are,
you have to believe on some level things
aren't changing. Okay, good. If you
believe things are coming this way, you
know, and I ask you, do you believe they
never change? You say, no, of course I
know things change, but not really. If
the thing exists from its own side, it
could not change. It would never change.
It could not change. If it's not coming
from your
seeds, what's a seed? Why do things
change? Your seeds change. You know,
when the seed makes the tree, what
happens to the seed? It's gone. The seed
gives its energy to the tree, energy to
the tree, and then the tree uses the
energy to grow, and then the tree dies.
Okay? If if things come from your seeds,
they can be impermanent. They can die.
Okay. But if they don't come from your
seeds, why should they change? Okay. If
they're coming this way, what can make
them change? Okay. So, she's accusing
him. You're the guy who thinks nothing
changes. And he's like, I don't I never
said that. Yeah, but you think it, you
believe that. Okay. Got it. Cool. All
right.
[Music]
Uh, and then he accused her of not
having any
friends. Okay? He accused her of not
having any friends. He accused her of
being a lonely
person. He accused her of never coming
home. Where's home?
In the human mind, you never show up.
You know, like once a year when you're
at Diamond Mountain in the middle of the
class, you think about emptiness and
then the rest of the time you're just
worrying about how much how irritating
somebody is. You see what I mean? So he
accused her of being a loner. She
doesn't have any friends. She never she
never even comes home to her husband
like that. Okay. Then what did she say?
It's not me who doesn't have friends.
It's you that don't have friends. Why?
Because all the friends you think you
have don't even
exist. Next time you get in a fight with
your
[Music]
husband, you can try
that. Probably just get confused. Uh
okay. If if things are not coming from
you, they can't exist. They number one
they cannot change and then number two
they couldn't exist anyway. Okay, you
know the two husbands in the kitchen,
right? Uh the husband who is hurting you
even though you didn't do anything.
There's no such thing. I didn't do
anything. We need Where's
Ayan when you need him? He's so good at
it. He's like I didn't do anything. I
think he must use it at home. I don't
know. Uh don't
die. Anyway,
uh yeah, the wife says, "My husband just
start yelling at me, but I didn't do
anything." Okay, in this system, if the
pen is coming from you, then the husband
is coming from you. The husband's saying
something to you is coming from you.
Okay? Then you're going to get upset.
Okay? All right? If you understand where
he's coming from, you can change it. If
you don't understand, he will last
forever. and he doesn't exist. Okay.
He's an thing that lasts forever and
doesn't exist. Pretty cool, right? All
right. Then she's, you know, she's he
told her, "You don't have any friends."
Okay. And she
says, "I'm friends with
everybody." Okay? I don't say I don't
have any friends.
Everyone in the world is my friend. I
get along with everybody. Who's talking?
Yeah. An angel who understands seeds,
you know. Everybody in the world is my
friend.
I I love everybody and they love me cuz
I'm real because I'm coming from seeds.
Okay? I have real relationships that
come from seeds. When I get into a
relationship, I take care of it
by honoring other people's
relationships. Okay? Like I don't yell
at my husband. I just be I honor the
relationship. I keep my promises and I
force him to keep his. Got it. Very
interesting. Okay. Uh therefore I get
along with everybody. It means if you
understand that things come from seeds,
you can be close to
everything because that's real. That's
the real world. That's the only real
world. Got it. It's not that pens come
from seeds. It's that everything comes
from seeds. If you don't understand
that, you are living in an unreal place.
You are living in a place that doesn't
exist. Okay? Then you're kind of crazy.
which means eight billion people are
crazy apparently or they're
Buddhists. I mean, I didn't say they
were, but I didn't say they weren't.
Okay, good. Now, next one. She says
she's on this idea of friendship. Okay.
And she's on this idea that people are
naturally friends.
Everyone's close to me because they
depend on me. Okay, we depend they
depend on me. How does the world depend
on me? Yeah, my sins. Okay, the world
depends on me. Don't tell me I don't
have any friends. You know, next time
your husband says that, don't tell me I
don't have any friends. I have lots of
friends. Everything depends on me
because my mind is making everything.
Okay,
now I think here's a $100 question.
Everybody's
like, "Okay, here we
go." She He says, "You're a loner.
You're a loser. You don't have any
friends. You show up in the mine once a
year when you go to Diamond Mountain for
five
minutes, you know, and mostly you're
just out there on your own. You don't
have any friends." Okay. He accuses her.
Then she says, "No, no, no. I'm friends
with everybody." And he says,
"Why? How?" And she says, "I'm friends,
everybody's friends with me because they
come from
me." Okay? Everybody's the pen and
everybody else comes from me. Therefore,
they like me. They're friend. They're
friends of mine. Okay? Got it? Now,
that's called dependent.
dependence. Okay. But there's a deeper
idea you want to go there.
It's our
interdependence. Okay. I'll make it
simple.
Uh depend depends on your
seats. You want it super simple or kind
of simple?
Kind of simple.
Okay. The pen depends on your seats.
Therefore, the pen is your friend. But
you, sorry, you're the friend of the pen
because without you, the friend can't be
there. Okay, got it. But
uh he's also your
friend. The pen is also your friend.
It's a inter
tendel some pretentious some would
bother interdependence. It's not
dependent origination. It's
interdependent origination. The seed,
the tree depends on Listen, I'll make it
simple. 100 bucks. The tree depends on
the seed and the seed depends on the
tree. But how can that be the tree came
after the seed? $100.
Your your seed created the picture of
the tree and the seed and then you your
seed your mental picture relates them as
a cause and effect.
Good. Yeah, I'll refine it a little bit.
Okay. The seed creates the tree
obviously, but the tree also creates the
seed because you cannot call
uh can you call uh
Can you cannot call a seed the cause of
the tree before the tree exists. Nice
$100. Thank you.
Uh, your seeds made the pen, but your
pen made the seeds
seeds. Okay. Your seeds made the pen,
but the pen made the seeds seeds.
That's that's real dependent
origination. Mutual. Mutual. Both ways.
Everybody's going like this. Oh, I made
the I made the pen. I made the pen. But
the pen made your
cease because they can't be seas until
they make
something. Got it. Diamond way. Diamond
mountain. Diamond wear student says it's
all the pen is all
C and everybody else knows the secret.
Okay, normal normal DCI
student. Everything comes from the
seeds. Everything comes from the seeds.
Okay. Diamond mountain diamond way
master five house
master. Everything the pen come from me.
The pen come from my seats. Got it. New
mudra.
Okay, I make the pen and the pens come
from my seeds and my seeds are seeds
because of the pen. Okay, it it's when
you think about dependent urgentation,
it's both ways. Okay, and that's deeper
and they don't usually teach it. People
don't usually teach it, but it's true.
$500 even
[Music]
wor. What's the ancient example for that
seed thing?
Okay, Ella's got it. Uh, the the port
like a triangle. The the spheres.
Spears. Good. Spears. 500. Yeah.
[Applause]
Okay. In ancient language, they call it
the spear example. Spear example. Okay.
So, in the ancient war, they don't have
guns. They have
spears. And at the tip of the spear,
they put later they put metal. They have
a stick and they have metal on the tip
and they throw the spear at people.
Right? Even in a war, you got to take a
break for breakfast or lunch. Okay? So
there's kind of an agreement during
these terrible ancient battles. They all
say, "Let's just take off for lunch.
Let's take a lunch break." And they all
run back to their camp and they start a
fire and they start cooking something.
And they always No, no good
fighter puts their spear on the ground
because then the metal will get rusty
and it will break. Okay? So they always
pile their
spears like this and they support each
other. Two, it takes two guys to put the
spears. They have to support their
spears. What's the
example? Yeah. The pen depends on
the seeds and the seeds depend on the
pen. It's mutual mutual interdependent
mutual dependence. Okay. You got to
remember that. Okay.
Your husband comes from you, but you
also come from your
husband because there's no you without
your husband to come from
you.
Okay? And and by the way, when you have
trouble with another person,
uh you're messing around with this
relationship. You you something's wrong.
It's obviously it's a problem if you
think the other person doesn't come from
you. But you also have to understand
that you come from them. So if you're
always accusing someone you're messed
up, then what are you really saying? I'm
messed up. Okay, it goes both ways.
Okay, it's
very it's really true because the tree
defines the
seed. If another
person that you that you have a
relationship is messed up, that's a
proof that you're messed up. Okay? And
that's hard. That's a hard thing to, you
know, if someone tells you all the
you ever met were coming from
you, you're
like, and then they say because it's a
reflection of you, you're
like, and then they define you. And then
you're like, oh, super
Okay. All right. Cool. Uh, everybody
says, "I want to study Diamond Way." Ga,
I don't want philosophy. If I wanted
philosophy, I would have come to the
12-year alarm
room. Uh, I just want Diamond Way. Okay?
I'm giving you just Diamond Way. Okay?
All right.
Understand? Okay. All right.
Uh, so what she's arguing, what's
happening
here, you got to get in the mood of the
argument. The whole book is an argument.
Okay? The angel's arguing with the
devil, and he says, "You're such a
loser. You know, you come home, you're
always alone. You know, you come home
once a year. I see you once a year. You
you make me think for five minutes that
the husband might be coming for me and
then I forget it. You know, you're never
here. Why should I listen to you're so
lonely? You're such a lonely person. And
she's like, I'm not lonely. You're the
lonely one. I'm friends with everybody
who lives in this
planet because they are the tree and I
am the
seed. They make me who I
am. Gunning. It's very deep. You pen
guys, go back to
DCI. You seed guys, the pen makes your
seed seeds. Okay. Appre thank the pen.
Thank you pen. Pen's like, "Thank
you." You know, if I wasn't for your
seeds, I wouldn't be here. Then you have
to say, "But without you, I wouldn't
have seeds because they wouldn't be
seeds because they didn't make
anything." Understand?
The real dependent origination ingual is
back and forth. It's both ways. Okay?
Got
it? Which means she is never alone and
she knows it. Okay? If you understand
dependence, you are deep friends with
every other person on this
planet. And every other planet, by the
way, but I don't want to blow your head
up. Okay? I'll say it again. If you
really understand the
pen, then you are friends. You are
connected to every person on this planet
automatically. If you understand the
pen, every person in the world is your
friend. You depend on each other. Don't
tell me I'm lonely cuz I only show up in
the brain once a year. I agree. But all
day I'm friends with everybody and
you're
not. Okay, got it. He's not. Who's he?
Yeah. Ignorance or whatever.
Misunderstanding.
Okay. Then she goes on to a
very sexy list. She's bragging now.
You're the loser. Who? Ignorance. You're
lonely. You sitting the head by
yourself. Okay. I got friends. I got so
many friends. You don't even know. Okay.
Then he's like, "Well, who? Who? Tell me
who." Then she starts. Okay. Here's a
list of my friends. Okay. Here she
goes. The rising of the sun and the
rising of the moon. The sun and the moon
are my
buddies. Is that cool? Okay. Yeah. The
directions are my bodies. East and west.
Okay. They depend on me. Okay. got it.
She's bragging about how many friends
she's got. He accused her of being
friendless because she's such a loser.
And she's like, "Yeah, I'm a loser. I
got big I got friends in high places."
Where? The sun and the moon. And I got
east and west. Okay. I got east and
west. I got day and
night. Okay. They're my friends. Got it.
Okay. And summer, winter, autumn,
spring, the four
seasons. They're are my friends. Okay.
The fact that the rain falls down, the
fact that flowers grow and fruits grow
on the trees, they all come from me.
Okay. She's she's bragging about how
many friends she has. She's I got
everybody now. Stanley
$100. Then you could buy another
statute. Uh I mean part of another the
finger.
Uh he's not going to answer anyway. It's
okay. This is the discussion of borders.
She's really talking about borders.
Okay. She's saying my friends are the
border between night and day. My friends
are the border between east and west. My
friends are the border between winter
and summer. In the ancient Sanskrit,
[Laughter]
simma. Oh, did I tell you there's that's
$50.
And what's the Tibetan for sema?
Sam. Okay, it's s. Say
uh so there's two words you should
learn. Okay, it's a the Tibetan is sam
ts a
m and the the Sanskrit for sam is sema
long i sa. Okay, sema. And sema means a
border. And uh it goes into English
as Yeah. the seam uh like the seam this
stitching here this seam this this where
they where they sew their cloth together
that's called in English a seam it comes
from ancient Sanskrit which is sema okay
su comes from that sutra comes from that
okay string uh okay sema so what does
sema mean sema became to mean the border
okay seem came to mean the border and
it's very very important for a retreat
center. Okay. It's a big big important
thing for a retreat center. And every
time we do a retreat, silent retreat,
serious retreat, we draw a border. We
make a border. We make two
borders. David knows the
two. Say, "Gisha, how much
money?" Two borders at
least. Yeah. One. Yeah. One one is, you
know, somebody runs up that mountain and
and puts a stick. It's called
samto. Or you can put a piece of paper
on your door. Or you should do both.
That's kind of an inner circle. There
are more circles. We're not going to
talk about them, but this is sema. Sema
means uh say,
it's a long sea. Yeah. It means the
border. And I I was telling the people
in Denuang when I did three-year
retreat, Ellie remembers I was in the
car. I was finishing the diamond cutter
business book in the car, the last page.
And I said, we get to the gate of the
three-year retreat. I say,
"Stop." Then I I gave her the manuscript
to give to the publisher. And then I I I
walk we park the car, walk through and I
turn around and I it's a cow gate. It's
a wooden cowgate. And I take the cowgate
and I close it and I say I won't leave
this gate for three years. It's a weird
feeling, right? You guys who did three
years, you know the feeling. You're like
three years, you got this doubt you
should let go or
not. Now I let go, you know? And I said,
"Okay, I will not go out of
this gate for three years." And we
didn't. And it was weird things
happened. I told a funny story in
Dunang. I broke one tooth really bad in
one of the other retreats like I'm like
I got to I got to go to town. I got to
get a a dentist. And they said, "Gisha,
you never heard of
superglue?" And I'm like, "What?" And
they're like, "We'll just super glue
it." And I'm like, "But the tooth is
gone. I don't know where it is. They're
half there." They said, "No, no, we'll
fill it in with superglue." And I'm
like, "Okay, let's try." You know, and
so I didn't break the sema. I didn't go
across the sea for three years, three
months, three days. Okay. Uh, so there's
this idea in the angel and the devil
talk right here of Sema. Okay. But here
the sema is what's the line between sun
and
moon? What's the line between pen and
seeds? What's the line between east and
west? I we used to have a project in
Mexico across the border in Douglas. You
know a
pria. We used to have a pro we tried to
type Tibetan there. All the computers
got
stolen. We did. We really did. And uh I
said, "I got to go down. I'm going to do
something." And I was going over across
the border to talk to the workers and
and I said, "Uh, wait a minute." I told
the policeman, "Can I just do something?
One thing." And he's like, "What? They
don't trust you for anything." And I'm
like, "Just for fun. I want to put one
foot in the United States and one foot
in Mexico, and I want to see how it
feels." I'm like, you know, I'm like,
Then I'm standing there and I'm looking
down the border, you know. And I said,
you know what? It feels just the same,
you know. I don't feel anything. I don't
feel any border, you know. I don't see
any border. It's just dirt. It's desert
actually, you know. It's just dirt. I
don't
see. But it's a karmic line, right?
People on this side, many people are
hungry. And
then six feet away, 2 meters away, the
people have too much food. They're all
dying of uh
overweight. Really? So these people are
hungry. These people are dying of over.
Who made the
border? Is it like some politician make
a
border? You know, your your seats make
the border. Your seats make the border.
So what she's saying is borders are my
friend.
border between you and other people. The
border between your eye and the pen, the
border between me and
you. This all coming from seeds. The
borders are coming from seeds. The sema
are coming from seeds. Got it? She's not
just saying, "Oh, you know, sun and moon
come from me. East and west come from
me. Day and night come from me. Winter
summer come from me. She's not saying
that. She says you make the minds. You
make the
minds. By the way, if everybody
understood that, there would be a very
strange language would develop.
Me David went to Dunwang so that David
me could have a a conference so that
David me could translate for the Chinese
English Chinese
Chinese and then you know like that like
the you'd have to change all human
languages all human languages are based
on
misperception the word you and the word
me is a mistake it's it's not that if
you're a nice person you should think of
me as you. That's not
true. That's wrong. There shouldn't be
any you and there shouldn't be any me.
We should have lunch or we shouldn't
have
lunch no matter where's the border. Got
it? I am you and you are me. Therefore,
if you understand that, can the partner
in your head say you don't have any
friends? Then you're like, "You don't
understand, man. I'm the only one who's
a friend to everybody." Got it? The
angel says, "You're the loser. You're
the lonely one. You're the one with no
friends. You don't realize you can't
exist without other people. You are
other people." Okay, got it? It's very
powerful. It's very powerful. That's why
it took us like 10 years to get this
far. We like did one
verse. Okay. Right?
Then now when you think of friend wisdom
says you know understanding seeds
understanding the pen says I got real
friends and you don't even know what
friends
are I got such good friends they're
me got it don't say I don't have any
friends I I it's true I don't have
friends I am my friends and they are me
And that's how close we are. And and
then if you understand that your life is
awesome, your life is every day is a is
is really
fun. Recognizing that you are other
people is is a is is fun all day long.
That never stops. Okay. You can be goofy
all day. Okay. All right. Okay. All
right. Really? Okay. And that's fun.
Okay. I mean, even if all this stuff is
philosophy, I don't care. If you want to
have fun all day, every day, that's
fun. That's real fun. You just have fun
on a birthday or something. That's just
once a
year. What's a deep gisha
wisdom? Yeah. Somebody asked me how many
students you want. I said 365 with
different
birthdays. My wife says, "Don't eat
dessert." I said, "I somebody had a
birthday. I got to eat, you
know."
Yeah. Okay. So, the borders come from
you. All the borders come from you.
Maybe they're not so useful.
uh and they relate directly to retreat
because the word for retreat in in the
ancient language simma in Sanskrit or
sam in Tibetan is border and it means to
stay inside the border that's a
different kind of border that
means sometimes you can think clearer if
you're not around a hundred people you
know like if you have a family if you
work you have a normal life that's Good.
Other people are sweet. To be with other
people is sweet, but sometimes to be
alone in your retreat, Kevin, is really
cool. And then when you get out, you
know what? I don't know, John Brady. Uh,
I had this thing in retreat. I remember
looking at the window. I distinctly
remember looking at the window and
saying this is not
fun to to sit here for a thousand days.
I didn't have a toilet. I didn't have wa
running water. I didn't have
electricity. I was in a desert, you
know, and I was like, this is not fun.
And I'm thinking, why? There's nobody
else to help.
and and I I
can't have that fun of helping somebody,
you know, and I felt lonely. I was
like, this is cool. I mean, retreat is
cool, but I don't get a chance to make
dinner for anybody. I don't get a chance
to say hi to anybody. I don't get a
chance to talk to anybody. I don't get a
chance to serve people. So I think one
reason to go into
retreat and you guys are going to do a
deep retreat for four
days four days. Uh you will start to
miss other people. You know the first
day is cool. I finally got rid of that
guy who can't talk. He talks all day.
You know then like the third day you're
like I kind of miss him. You know and
you'll feel a little bit lonely. And
during those times, that's the time to
think about uh being a bodhic sappa. And
and when you're in deep retreat for a
long time by
yourself, you will understand how much
you need other people and and and what a
how much fun and how sweet it is to have
other people to serve. Okay. Okay. And
it doesn't matter whether they're nice
people or bad people. Serving bad people
is more fun than serving nice
people. Okay. It's an art form. Advanced
art. Okay. All
[Music]
right. Then she goes dark. How much time
I got,
Tim? Okay. Then she goes dark. Okay. And
it's a little dark, you know. She
suddenly flips. She suddenly goes
somewhere else. Okay. Uh, I'm on I'm
still on verse 337, you guys.
Uh, she says there's a border
between spring, summer, winter, fall.
Okay, that's okay. And then she says
there's a border called alive and dead.
And then she starts to get dark, you
know, and you're like, what?
Yeah.
She's like, "There's another border,
okay? And it's called life and death,
okay?" And then she said, "There's other
divisions. You can be sick or you can be
in active
agony. You can be suffering at Diamond
Mountain in the same week from excessive
heat and excessive cold.
As far as toilet seats, I'll go for the
heat. All
right. I mean, not okay. Uh, hunger on
one hand, thirst on the other hand, and
everything else. Okay. So, she's she
suddenly transitions to other borders
between pain, between aging, death.
She's going to the four area truth.
She's going to the truth of suffering.
She's
saying I also created the
lines between the four truths. I created
the line between pain and the cause of
pain. I created the line between nirvana
and the causes the path. I created those
lines. I created the lam rim. I created
those lines. Okay? You did between life
and death. Okay?
So if you understand those lines are
coming from you, you can change them. If
you don't understand they're coming from
you, you cannot change them.
Okay, cool. You if you understand where
the sem what's that borders come from,
you can change the border between life
and death.
Okay. It's tantric class. Okay. I get to
say what I
want. Somebody me and Si were working on
a special project uh about you know
helping people do the second half of
their life. How what are you going to do
during the second half of your life? You
know like this kind of thing. We're
developing an idea. And then
um I was teaching something like that
uh for for the
DSU and uh somebody said to me, "Oh, uh
so you're teaching a second half of
life." And and I said, "No, I'm teaching
the first half of what comes
next." Okay? And they're like, "Huh?"
And I said, I'm not I'm not interested
in teaching you how to get old and get
your kidney disease and then die. I'm
not, you know, to me that's not very
interesting. I'm teaching you the next
two halves of your life, which is what
happens after that. You know, how do you
transition? It's not like how do you go
grow old
gracefully? you know, don't forget to I
don't know, do your stretches or else
you won't be able to walk or something
like that.
Okay, that's that's just the first half.
The second half is what happens after
that.
Okay, if you start a new project when
you're
40, that's the first half of your new
life. Okay? And then we have to master
the art of the second half.
which is after your death. Okay? So
don't think of life as
uh first half and second half of my
life. Don't think like that. The second
half of your life is the first
half. Okay? Then what happens? You die
and then you have another half. Okay?
And if you study well, if you learn to
do retreat, well, if you study diamond
way, well, it's amazing fun. It's
awesome. It's super cool. Do you know
what color the sky is going to be in my
next
life? Peach
color. Okay, it's the only one better
than blue.
Okay. Like imagine you could uh be
planning uh your next
childhood, your next teenage
years, you know, like that. Imagine you
could be planning them now. Okay, that's
what we're talking about. And you can
say either Gisha's crazy or he knows
something. Okay, and I don't to me it
doesn't care if you if you think I'm
crazy. I don't mind, you know. If you
want to give away the $100, I'm okay.
Now, maybe I'm crazy or maybe I know
something. Okay. All right. I mean, it's
possible. We have to say
what? Either he knows something
or maybe he does, maybe he he doesn't.
Okay. All right. Cool. Anyway, I'm
looking forward. Uh I'll see you in the
next world. Don't be late.